maybe maybe maybe people's faith in my
use of Linux will be restored so my
video about um Linux on the desktop
making me fat is already got more hate
on it than it does positive uploads
which I expected because most people
don't even watch to the end of the video
but in order in order to prove my love
for Linux let me I want to Proclaim
something to you I was using Geeks in
2020 before you were born
so
there and I absolutely love Geeks guix I
think it's super awesome do I use it
every day no and that's what this video
is about what do I think of Geeks and
why you should or shouldn't use it okay
uh these are these are questions that
people ask me frequently because they
see me using Linux and they you know
they have all kinds of opinions about
that Linux people tend to have lots of
opinions and that's fine that's great
that's what we love we love the passion
I totally I don't I don't always love
the pass
because sometimes I'm on the other side
of it and um so what is Geeks let's talk
about that really quickly um and I'll
tell you as usual I'll tell you a story
so in 2020 uh actually it was it was
right before Co it was either right
before it was right it was it was before
Co had really hit hard um I went to O
Linux Meetup and I strongly encourage
everybody to go to Linux me to talk
about that in another video building
your professional Learning Network and
your profession profal Network in
general and how and several people got
jobs from these meetups including the
guy with $100,000 starting salary
another assisted man several coding and
C uh I helped all these people go
discover these Linux meetups and go to
these meetups and I encouraged these
particularly younger people to
participate and and I had adults in the
industry coming up to me and saying oh
my god um so I I would co-present with
some of these with some of these and I
mean kids some of them are 10 11 12 and
they they were all like little Aaron
schwarzes a lot of them they're just
absolutely brilliant autodidactic
engineers and I totally love being
around them and and so the Geeks so Bari
came in a video
[Music]
barari is actually I have a really good
memory barari is actually in our stream
and is one of my French friends viewers
um that actually we we geeked out like a
long time ago probably four or years ago
around that same time frankly and and we
did um totally geek out about you know
all things 80s and everything and and
this video was was prompted because
marari is saying that they're learning
Geeks and and emacs right now and I'll
do a separate video on emac um but I I
just wanted to mention that I actually
really think Geeks is a great idea and I
first experienced Geeks at a at a Linux
Meetup where somebody presented it and I
was like damn this is really really cool
you know the ability to layer on
configurations on top of each other and
just the overall ease with which you can
you know patch a system and keep it up
to date I absolutely love it I I do I
think it's a fantastic thing and one of
the great things about the Linux
Community is you can be on the bleeding
edge and you can experiment with these
things um and I mean a lot of the a lot
of the video that if I were going to do
a video about Arts it's a lot of the
same ideas I want I love Innovation and
since the you know since the 90s when
I've been using Linux I have frequently
had to make a decision about how edgy do
I get in my use of Linux and that's what
this video is really about it's not
about necessarily Geeks it's about how
edgy you want to be and when that might
serve you and when it's going to work
against you and that's the real core
Crux of this video it's not about Geeks
I will mention Geeks in the title to get
people to watch it but the real
principle here is you know I use Arch by
the way right people use that all the
time they joke about it because it's not
easy to learn Arch and you learn a lot
by using Arch same thing would go for
geeks right um it's not easy to learn
Geeks it's it's easier than Arch but um
it's not easier to build your own system
with Linux from scratch I mean District
people always have fun with this whole
topic and I don't want to go down that
rabbit hole I really don't the the the
bottom line line is if you are in a
position where you don't need to get a
job or you're not trying to uh
supplement your current job with the the
skills that you probably should have as
a foundation then yeah have go to town
have fun play with geeks play with all
the stuff that that doesn't matter in in
the Enterprise and and I when I say
those words I immediately get people who
are going to downvote me the same people
who downvoted me saying Linux on the
desktop sucks and made me fat are the
kind of people that are going to
downvote me for telling you that some of
you are going to be wasting time by
learning Geeks they don't want to hear
it or Arch they they don't want to hear
that they are so dogmatically
religiously obsessed with Linux that
they cannot step separate themselves
from it and stand back and look at these
things as
tools or a or as you know Pursuits for a
hobbyist if you want to be and that se
that ability to not separate yourself is
extremely dangerous it's downright toxic
so the message here is yes please use
Geeks it's an amazing operating system
it's super duper cool but if you don't
know how to configure and maintain and
manage an RPM system a red hat system as
ugly and horrible and corporate and
corrupt as it is and it really is right
I had pedora stock I'm sorry I had redot
stock before Fedora was a thing and I
sold all my stock because out out of
disgust for the Fedora thing that
happened back in
200 whatever two or one or something
maybe it was even 99 I don't remember
because because I was with you I was
with you I agree I agree that some of
the you know the corporate Shields that
are taking over the Linux Community I
agree that that is a part of it but but
we got to stay balanced here there's
also been a lot of good that's happened
that from from these organizations that
come in control that is not what this
video is about this video is about is
Geeks worth learning and the answer is
for most of you no it's not Geeks is not
worth learning it's going to be at best
an entertaining distraction uh and at
worst it's going to keep you from
maintaining or learning the skills you
need to get a job every day so if you
don't know red hat like we mentioned if
you don't know how to administer and
maintain and install auntu um and and I
would argue those are the two main ones
but it's even more valuable for you to
learn the suie Linux Dro than it is to
you learn the other ones so Geeks is a
great Dr it's really cool um I one of
the things I think is the most positive
about it I want to end on a positive
note is Geeks is really cool for a
container to throw right because you can
do some really fun things with it if I
if I actually break away and find time
to play around with geeks when I'm not
you know preparing to ride across
America on my bike
um which is way more fun to me than
playing around with random Linux
technology that I don't want to spend my
time in my spare time today uh doing
these things I want to maintain the
skills that are going to keep me
employed and through retirement so my
priorities are different than yours but
if you are one of these people who likes
to play around and Dabble and not go
outside it's a joke don't get mad um so
fine fine you know go play around you
know to your heart's content play around
with geeks see what happen s and maybe
you'll be ready in 10 years when it
finally hits mainstream when people try
to actually use it right and because
that's about how long it takes and to be
fair as well I did Linux was not even
used in the Enterprise when I started
using Linux using Linux anywhere in the
Enterprise I actually recommended
there's a story about this that's
related I recommended I was I was
running the internal uh internet
internet for nike.com I got an award for
it and all this stuff but I set it up
and I went to the I went to the IT
people I went to the infrastructure
systems administrators I was just the
web person then and I said look wouldn't
it be great if we could run Linux here
we wouldn't have to pay the money for
the Solaris license you know what they
told me oh no oh no we can't do that we
can't have that I said you know there's
this project called Apache it's free and
we don't have to pay the licenses for
Netscape server Enterprise server I know
I'm dating myself there you know what
they said oh no we want to have that and
I said okay and I kind of like went back
to to my little you know because I had I
was running an entire Linux server in my
garage the point I'm trying to make is I
get that there is a time and a place to
be edgy and to experiment and to learn
and to promote and build the
technologies that are going to become
mainstream Technologies tomorrow
absolutely I totally am down with that
that's why I think Geeks is so cool but
I but it depends on where you are and if
you're trying to break in and get a job
that I mean if you if you have if you're
looking at Geeks and you're playing with
it in your garage or something I mean
the equivalent um then great that should
be a supplemental you know line item on
your raising make sure you put that
stuff on your rais me by the way playing
around with geeks in your spare time in
your lab is a great raume bullet because
that's a way for you to say hey look I
actually really love Linux to the point
where I use my own free time to to see
where it's going to go and to become
experimental with things and I have a
lab and I know how to set up a lab and I
I know I ALS but but I also have you
know I also have app skills and RPM
skills and blah blah blah I know how to
do these things as well because that's
what they're going to pay you for
they're going to pay you to maintain and
the systems and know how to build
containerization systems and BMS and all
that stuff that are using the tools of
the day the tools of that are mainstream
at that point that were edgy 10 years
ago and I mean 10 years ago we are now
using Linux as a standard it's now
becoming a desktop option it's now 2024
okay and IBM was kind of ahead of the
curve letting me use Linux on the
desktop in
2005 and I did I ran Linux on my desktop
for 10
years right so but but you know using
using Enterprise Linux even as a server
in 1998 was unheard of you know so Geeks
GUI X is the is the way to spell it so
um so I do think you should play with it
I think you should put on your resume I
think it will prove that you are really
committed to Linux and and understanding
it and exploring the many different
amazing things by the same token I think
you should play around with BSD I I
would actually think I would argue very
seriously that understanding BSD inside
and out is far more valuable than guix
in fact I would suggest that BSD is a
more significant operating system than
Linux I know I'm going to get hatte for
that but it is that the things that are
being done with BSD there's more BSD in
router devices and things like that that
matter than Linux I mean Linux is behind
containerization and a bunch of other
stuff but I'm not going to have the BSD
versus Linux bite we're not going to do
that bite right now we'll do a separate
video for that but the point is is that
should you learn Geeks yes you should
but not right now and not if you're
trying to get a job unless you want to
really really dive in and say I want to
do this s extra so it's kind of a
wishy-washy answer um what do I think of
it I think it's freaking amazing I
really sincerely do I think it's
fantastic and I look forward to using it
to practice building uh quick and dirty
disos particularly in containers and
things like that but I have no immediate
need for that and that's why I haven't
been playing with it bottom line I don't
have the time to play with that I need
to get good with anable playbooks right
now because I need to deliver on an
automatic deployment that's being
triggered through an anable Playbook
that's being called through a web hook
these are all things that I have to
learn and do today that I'm about to
turn the video off and go learn and do
and Implement and when my time at work
is being my 68 hours a day is being
spent doing those things I don't have
time to play around with geeks because
at 5 o' I'm going to get on my bike and
practice biking for three hours so that
I can practice crossing the country if I
if I was still trying to break in and
get a job and everything maybe I would
allocate those that time those six hours
or whatever to learning Geeks and that's
a great thing so just know where you are
uh before before you do that if you do
not if you have not fully uh
comprehended how to minister and
maintain that includes understanding the
startup scripts um and you know the way
that services are run and all of that
inside of obuntu server and red hat then
I would suggest spending time making
sure you understand those Technologies
if your priority is on getting and
maintaining a job and my videos as you
already know are primarily focused on
that above all um there are tons of
other people covering all the crazy
stuff that's fun to play with but
doesn't really relate to an actual job
and I want my channel to my content to
be very very particular about what's
relevant in the industry and frankly
Geeks isn't it's just not in fact please
please please save the hate and if you
know of anybody using Geeks in an
Enterprise capacity for a company that's
being traded on the open stock market
not some tiny little edgy silicon valet
company if you know of any major
corporations or organizations that are
using Geeks today for production systems
and they're not exploring it please
please let me know I really really want
to know
okay thanks thank you for everybody for
that video I got to go to work now and
you know make money